The Life Of Muhammadﷺ, Madinan Period Volume 2
By Imam Anwar Al_Awlaki,
اَعُوْذُ بِاللهِ مِنَّ الشِّيْطَانِ الرَّجِيْمِ۝
بِسْمِ اللهِ الرَّحْمَانِ الرَّحِيْمَ۝
اَلْحَمْدُ لله ، وَالصَّلَاةُ وَالسَّلَامُ عَلى سَيِّدِنَا محمد وَعَلَى اَلِهِ وَصَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ تَسْلِيْمًا كَثِيْرا
السلام وعليكم ورحمة الله وبركاته
When Ali Ibn Abi Talib رضي الله عنه was in Yemen,
there were some rumors surrounding his authority as an Ameer(أمير) over there.
Ali Ibn Abi Talib رضي الله عنه had some camels of Sadaqah(صدقه) with him
and the members of his army, they wanted to use these camels for transport.
Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي بن أبي طالب) refused.
And he had some work to do.
So, he left deputy to take care of affairs in his absence.
And when he came back, he found out that the camels were used for transport
because he saw the marks of the saddles on them.
And he also saw that the people were wearing some of the garments that were also given as part of Sadaqah(صدقه).
So, Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) became very angry, and he ordered that they take off those garments,
and they give them back and that caused some rumors.
And someone went back to Rasool Allah ﷺ to report what happened
and there was one of the Sahabah(صحابه) that was there,
and when this man was reporting these things against Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب)
the other Sahabi(صحابي) was saying: Yes, that's right.! Yes, that's right.!
And this Sahabi(صحابي) used to say that I used to dislike Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب), I used to hate him.
And Rasool Allah ﷺ when he saw him saying: Yes, that's right,
approving the complaints that were against Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب).
Rasool Allah ﷺ put his hand on the knee of this Sahabi(صحابي) and he told him;
Do you dislike Ali(علي)?
He said: Yes.
Rasool Allah ﷺ told him: You should love him.
So, this Sahabi(صحابي) said after that, Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) was among the most beloved to me.
So, this was the situation.
So when Rasool Allah ﷺ was returning from Hajjat-Ul-Widaa(حجةالوداع).
And he arrived in a place called Ghadeer Khumr(غدير خمر).
Rasool Allah ﷺ gathered the people and delivered to them the famous statement.
مَنْ كُنْت مَوْلَاهُ فِعْلِيٌّ مَوْلاهُ
If I am the friend of someone, then Ali(علي) is also his friend.
Mola(مولا) is friend, protector, close associate, so all of these statements to apply to Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب).
Now, the Shia(شيعه) they carried this too far and they took it out of the context.
The context of what happened is that
there were false rumors going against Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب),
so Rasool Allah ﷺ wanted to defend the reputation of Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) in front of everyone
and to let everyone know the status of Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب)
being the cousin of Rasool Allah ﷺ,
the husband of his daughter and the father of the only lineage remaining from Rasool Allah ﷺ
because no lineage remained from Rasool Allah ﷺ except through Al-Hassan Wal Hussain(ألحسن والحُسين),
the grandchildren of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ was telling the people that
if I am your Mola(مولا) than Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) is also your Mola(مولا).
If you love me, then you need to love Ali Ibn Abi Talib رضي الله عنه.
Rasool Allah ﷺ returned to Madina.
And now we're entering into the 11th year of Hijrah(هجرى) spent there the month of Muharram(محرم).
And in Safar(صفر), Rasool Allah ﷺ appointed Osama Bin Zaid(اسامه بن زيد) to lead an army
that is to be sent to the land of Balqaa(بلقاء) in Ash-Sham(الشام).
And the instructions were for Osama Bin Zaid(اسامه بن زيد);
To step with his horses on the land where his father was killed.
So, you can see now, that the focus of Rasool Allah ﷺ is on the boundaries with the Roman Empire.
You have Mo'ta(مؤته) first and then you have the Tabook(تبوك).
And now you have this army of Osama Bin Zaid(اسامه بن زيد),
in addition to the Sarayah(سراية) that were also sent into that area.
So, this happened in Safar(صفر).
Now, Osama Bin Zaid(اسامه بن زيد) at that time, how old was he?
He was between 18 to 20 years old, very young.
And you have seniors Sahabah(صحابه) from Al-Muhajireen(ألمهاجرين) and Al-Ansaar(ألأنصار),
older men with much experience in warfare and in leadership, and managing the affairs of armies
and Rasool Allah ﷺ appoints a very young man to lead an army that included Abu Bakr(ابو بكر) and Umar(عمر).
So, there was some talk going on.
And now, see the community is large for so there's more room for idle talk to go on,
because you still had a strong presence of Nifaq(نفاق) and large number of Muslims.
So, there was talk going around.
Why is Osama Bin Zaid(اسامه بن زيد) appointed?
For two reasons the objections were two reasons,
Number one, his age
and Number two, that he belongs to the slave caste.
I mean, his father was a former slave and his mother's same thing, Umm Aimen(أم أيمن).
Therefore, how could he lead over the free men?
And these concerns reach to Rasool Allah ﷺ.
So, Rasool Allah صلوات الله وسلام عليه said, and this is in Bukhari(ألبخاري)
إنْ تَطْعَنُوا في إمارَتِهِ فقَدْ كُنْتُمْ تطَعَنون في إمارَةِ أبِيهِ مِن قَبْلِهِ،
If you are disputing his appointment,
then you have disputed the appointment of his father before.
وَاَيْمُ اللَّهِ لقَدْ كانَ خَلِيقًا لِلْإِمارَةِ، وإنْ كانَ مِن أحَبِّ النَّاسِ إلَيَّ، وإنَّ هذا لَمِنْ أحَبِّ النَّاسِ إلَيَّ بَعْدَهُ
And In the name of Allah, and now he's talking about his father, Zaid Bin Harissa(زيد بن حارثة).
He was suitable person for appointing as a leader,
and he was one of the most beloved people to me.
And this man is one of the most beloved people to me, after him.
So, Osamah(اسامه), Rasool Allah ﷺ was saying that he took the position of his father after his father passed away.
In the month of Safar(صفر).
The beginning of the end was starting.
Rasool Allah ﷺ has received many Ayaat(آيات) and indications that he would die just like every other human being.
Allahعَزّوجَلّ revealed Ayaat(آيات) that warn, of the death of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
Allah سبحانه وتعالى says; And this was revealed in Makkah.
وَلَلْآخِرَةُ خَيْرٌ لَكَ مِنَ الْأُولَىٰ۝
وَلَسَوْفَ يُعْطِيكَ رَبُّكَ فَتَرْضَىَٰ۝
And the Hereafter is better for you than the first life
and your Lord is going to give you and you will be satisfied.
And therefore, when Rasool Allah ﷺ was given the choice of living in Duniyah(دنيا) or dying,
we will see what his choice was?
Because he has the promise from very early on in Makkah, that the afterlife is better for you.
And Allah will give you until you're satisfied and Allah سبحانه وتعالى says:
إِنَّكَ مَيِّتٌ وَإِنَّهُمْ مَيِّتُونَ ۝
ثُمَّ إِنَّكُمْ يَوْمَ الْقِيَامَةِ عِنْدَ رَبِّكُمْ تَخْتَصِمُونَ۝
Az-Zumar(إلزمر) Thirty-Thirty One(30-31);
Indeed, you are to die and indeed they are to die,
then indeed you on the Day of Resurrection before your Lord will dispute.
When Allahعَزّوجَلّ says in Surah Al-Ambiyaa(سورة الانبياء).
وَمَا جَعَلْنَا لِبَشَرٍ مِنْ قَبْلِكَ الْخُلْدَ
أَفَإِنْ مِتَّ فَهُمُ الْخَالِدُونَ۝
كُلُّ نَفْسٍ ذَائِقَةُ الْمَوْتِ
وَنَبْلُوكُمْ بِالشَّرِّ وَالْخَيْرِ فِتْنَةً ۖ وَإِلَيْنَا تُرْجَعُونَ۝
And we did not grant any man before you eternity.
So, if you die, would they be eternal, every soul will taste death,
and we test you with evil and with good as trial and to us, you will be returned.
So, the whole life is just a trial of good and bad, and everyone will die.
And Allahعَزّوجَلّ revealed to Muhammadﷺ during the Hajj(حَجْ) of Widaa(وداع).
اَلْيَوْمَ أَكْمَلْتُ لَكُمْ دِينَكُمْ وَأَتْمَمْتُ عَلَيْكُمْ نِعْمَتِي وَرَضِيتُ لَكُمُ الْإِسْلَامَ دِينًا۝
This day, I have perfected for you, your religion and completed my favor upon you
and have approved for you Islam as religion.
Now there's nothing directly here that indicates the death of Rasool Allah ﷺ
but there is an indication of the fulfillment of the mission.
And Allahعَزّوجَلّ says;
وَمَا مُحَمَّدٌ إِلَّا رَسُولٌ قَدْ خَلَتْ مِنْ قَبْلِهِ الرُّسُلُ
أَفَإِنْ مَاتَ أَوْ قُتِلَ انْقَلَبْتُمْ عَلَىٰ أَعْقَابِكُمْ ۚ
وَمَنْ يَنْقَلِبْ عَلَىٰ عَقِبَيْهِ فَلَنْ يَضُرَّ اللَّهَ شَيْئًا
وَسَيَجْزِي اللَّهُ الشَّاكِرِينَ ۝
وَمَا كَانَ لِنَفْسٍ أَنْ تَمُوتَ إِلَّا بِإِذْنِ اللَّهِ كِتَابًا مُؤَجَّلًا
وَمَنْ يُرِدْ ثَوَابَ الدُّنْيَا نُؤْتِهِ مِنْهَا وَمَنْ يُرِدْ ثَوَابَ الْآخِرَةِ نُؤْتِهِ مِنْهَا ۚ
وَسَنَجْزِي الشَّاكِرِينَ۝
Muhammad(محمد) is not but the Messenger, other Messengers have passed on before him.
So, if he was to die or be killed, would you turn back on your heels to unbelief,
and he, who returns back on his heels will never harm Allah at all.
But Allah will reward the Grateful.
And it is not possible for one to die except by permission of Allah at a decree determined
and whoever desires the reward of this world, we will give him their off.
And whoever desires the reward of the hereafter who will give him their off.
And we will reward the Grateful.
And Allahعَزّوجَلّ says;
بِسْمِ اللَّهِ الرَّحْمَٰنِ الرَّحِيمِ۝
إِذَا جَاءَ نَصْرُ اللَّهِ وَالْفَتْحُ۝
وَرَأَيْتَ النَّاسَ يَدْخُلُونَ فِي دِينِ اللَّهِ أَفْوَاجًا۝
فَسَبِّحْ بِحَمْدِ رَبِّكَ وَاسْتَغْفِرْهُ ۚ إِنَّهُ كَانَ تَوَّابًا۝
When the victory of Allah has come, and the conquest
and you see the people entering into the religion of Allah in multitudes
then exalt Him, with praise of your Lord and ask forgiveness of Him.
Indeed He is ever Accepting of repentance.
Again in these Ayaat(آيات), there is no indication, there's no direct indication of the death of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
Ibn Abbas(ابن عباس) used to sit with the senior Muhajireen(مهاجرين) and Ansaar(أنصار) in the court of Umar Ibn Al-Khattab رضي الله عنه.
So, some of the Muhajireen(مهاجرين) and Ansaar(أنصار) said, why is this young man sitting here,
when we have sons in his age, and they're not invited?
So, Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) wanted to point out to them, the reason.
So, he asked them: What do you understand from this Surah(سورة)?
Everyone gave an answer,
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) asked Ibn Abbas رضي الله عنه what do you understand from it?
He said: I understand from it, the death of Rasool Ullah.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) said: And that is what I understand from it.
And he made a point to the Sahabah(صحابه), who were there
that Ibn Abbas(ابن عباس) is sitting with us now, because of his knowledge, because of his understanding,
because of the Fiqh(فقه) and the deep understanding that he has of Islam
because this Surah(سورة) says; When the victory of Allah has come and the conquest
and the victory of Allah is the end result of Da'wah(دعوة).
So, it's towards the end.
وَالْعَاقِبَةُ لِلْمُتَّقِينَ۝
The end result belongs to the believers.
And you see the people entering into the religion of Allah in multitudes
and that was what is happening after Fateh Makkah(فتح مكه), People were entering in multitudes.
Then exalt Him with praise of your Lord and ask forgiveness of Him.
We usually ask Allah for forgiveness, when after we do the deed, then we ask Allah to forgive us.
So, after Salah(صلاة), what do you say.?
استغفرالله, استغفرالله, استغفرالله
after Hajj(حَجْ) same thing Astaghfirullah(استغفرالله).
So, Astaghfaar(استغفار) is something that comes towards the end
and this is an indication that the end of the life of Rasool Allah ﷺ is near
and Taubah(توبة) also comes towards the end.
There are also some Ahadith(احاديث) we talked about the Hadith(حديث) where,
when Rasool Allah ﷺ sent Muadh Ibn Jabal(معاذ ابن جبل) to Yemen
and told him you might not meet me anymore, and Muadh Ibn Jabal(معاذ ابن جبل) cried.
There is also the Hadith(حديث), where Rasool Allah ﷺ said in Hajj(حَجْ);
لِتَأْخُذُواعَنِّيْ مَنَاسِكَكُمْ، فَلَعَلِّيْ لَااَحُجْ بعد عَامِيْ هَذَه
Take from me your rituals, learn from me your rituals,
because I may never make Hajj(حَجْ) again after this time.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
إِنَّ جِبْرِيلَ كانَ يُعَارِضُنِي بالقُرْآنَ كُلَّ سَنَةٍ مَرَّةً، وإنَّه عَارَضَنِي به العَامَ مَرَّتَيْنِ، ولَا أُرَاهُ إلَّا اقتراب أجَلِي
Jibril(جبريل) used to recite Qur'an with me, every year once, they would go through the whole Qur'an.
And this year, he did it twice.
And I see that as an indication of the end of my life.
So, in the month of Safar(صفر) of the year 11 of Al-Hijrah(ألهجرة).
Rasool Allah ﷺ sent to Abu Mu'aihibbah(ابومويهبة), a servant of Rasool Ullah صلوات الله وسلام عليه.
And this was late at night,
so Rasool Allah ﷺ called, he woke up, Abu Mu'aihibbah(ابومويهبة) and called him and told him;
يَا أَبَا مُوَيْهِبَةَ إنِّيْ قَدْ أُمِرْتُ أَنْ أَسْتَغْفِرَ لِأَهْلِ هَذَا الْبَقِيَعْ فَانْطَلَقْ مَعِيْ
O Abu Mu'aihibbah(ابومو يهبة) I have been commanded to ask Allah to forgive, the people of Al-Baqiyah(البقيه), so come with me.
Al-Baqiyah(البقيه) is the cemetery of Madina,
the blessed cemetery, where the companions of Rasool Allah ﷺ, who struggled with him,
fought with him, supported him, were buried
and Rasool Allah ﷺ was ordered by Allah to go to the cemetery and ask Allah to forgive them.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ told Abu Mu'aihibbah(ابومو يهبة) to go with him.
So, they went together at night to Al-Baqiyah(البقيه) and when Rasool Allah ﷺ arrived there.
Subhaan Allah(سبحان الله) Rasool Allah ﷺ was going in the middle of the night
to the cemetery to give his Sahabah رضي الله عنهم a company.
He told them;
السلام عليكم يا اهل المقابر
Peace be upon you, O people of the graves.
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ told them, and look at these uplifting words for them.
لِيَهْنَأ لَكُمْ مَا أَصَبَحْتُمْ فِيْهِ مِمَّا أَصْبَحَ النَّاسُ فِيْهِ
Congratulations.
Rasool Allah ﷺ is congratulating the people of this cemetery, the people, who are dead.
Congratulations! That you do not experienced, what people here are experiencing.
Congratulations! That you passed away, in the early days of Da'wah(دعوة),
when the hearts were pure and the people were together and they were unified.
Congratulations! That you died in the difficult days when the rewards were great.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ is telling them that you are in a better position than who's left behind.
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
أَقْبَلَتْ اَلْفِتَنْ كَقِطْعَ اللَّيْلِ الْمُظْلِمْ، يَتْبَعُ آخِرُهَا أَوَّلَّهَا، وَالْآخِرَةُ شَرُّ مِّنَّ الْأُوْلَى
Trials and tribulations come like dark portions of the night following each other in succession.
The last been worse than the first.
Trials and tribulations are on their way and we are living in that time dear brothers and sisters.
We are living in the times of trials and tribulations, we're living in a time of Fitnah(فِتْنَه).
Fitnah(فِتْنَه) in Duniyah(دُنِيَّا) and Fitnah(فِتْنَه) in Deen(دين).
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ is congratulating, these Sahabah(صحابه), who died early and telling them,
congratulations that you died early,
because now the Fittan are coming like dark pieces of the night, one after the other.
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ looked at Abu Mu'aihibbah(ابومو يهبة) and said;
إِنِّيْ قَدْ أُعْطِيْتُ مَفَاتِيْحَ خَزَائِنِ الدُّنْيَا وَالْخُلْدَ فِيْهَا، ثُمَّ الْجَنَّةْ فَخُيِّرْتُ بَيْنَ ذَلِكَ وَبَيْنَ لِقَاءِ رَبِّيْ وَالْجَنَةْ
Rasool Allah ﷺ told Abu Mu'aihibbah(ابومويهبة)
I was given the choice of the keys of the treasures of Duniyah(دُنِيَّا) and living in Duniyah(دُنِيَّا) as long as it exists.
And then paradise, or
وَبَيْنَ لِقَاءِ رَبِّيْ وَالْجَنَةْ
Meeting my Lord or paradise.
So, the choice is you can live in Duniyah(دُنِيَّا), as long as this world would survive,
and you will be given the keys to the treasures of this world.
And then when you pass away, you will be in paradise, that's choice number one.
And the second choice is to meet Allah now and Jannah(جنة).
Abu Mu'aihibbah(ابومو يهبة) said: Choose us.
In one narration and in this narration he says;
Choose the keys of the treasures and living in Duniyah(دُنِيَّا) as long as it is living and then Jannah(جنة).
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: No! I have chosen to meet Allah and paradise.
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ sought forgiveness for the people of Al-Baqiyyah(البقيه) and then he left.
And when he arrived home the illness of his death began.
Rasool Allah ﷺ was not attached to Duniyah(دُنِيَّا).
Rasool Allah ﷺ his concern in Duniyah(دُنِيَّا) was his Ummah(امة),
his concern was not building, it was not wealth.
He didn't have attachment to Ad-Duniyah(دُنِيَّا) and therefore Ibn Kathir رضي الله عنه, He says;
فَاِنَّ الدُّنْيَا بِحاذَفِرِهَا كَانَتْ اَحْقَرَعِنْدَه’ كَمَا هِيَ عِنْدَالله ،
مِنْ اَنْ يَسْعی لَهَا اَوْ يُتْرُكْهَا بَعْدَه’ مِيْرَاثًا صَلَوَاتُ الله وَسَلَامُ عَلَيْه
He said; The Duniyah(دُنِيَّا) was so small in the eyes of Rasool Allah ﷺ and it is also small in the eyes of Allah
that Rasool Allah ﷺ left it, without leaving behind anything.
Ayesha رضي الله عنها was saying,
وَ رَاْسَى، وَرَاْسَى
My head hurts, My head hurts.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
بَلْ اَنَا ، وَرَاْسَه
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: No! It is me, who should say, my head hurts.
Rasool Allah ﷺ was having a severe headache and he was also having a severe fever
and the fever was so severe on Rasool Allah ﷺ,
when one of the companions put his hand on Rasool Ullah, he said;
I cannot leave my hand on you because of the heat.
I mean, it was very uncomfortable to touch the body of Rasool Allah ﷺ because of his fever
and the companion told Rasool Allah ﷺ;
انك لتوعك وعكا شديدا
You are going through very severe illness.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: Yes!
That is because we, the Prophets suffer double the suffering of everyone else.
Because Allahعَزّوجَلّ loves them.
Allahعَزّوجَلّ puts them through tougher tests,
because they are stronger and greater and better.
Allahعَزّوجَلّ puts them through tougher tests.
Rasool Allah ﷺ, one day wanted to go to the Masjid(مسجد)
لَعَلِّيْ اَحَدٌ عَلَى النَّاسْ
He wanted to give a covenant to the people.
So, he said gather for me seven buckets of water from seven different wells
and pour them on me, so that I can go out to the people.
So, they brought him this water and they were pouring this cold water on the body of Rasool Allah ﷺ to cool it down
because of the temperature
and to give Rasool Allah ﷺ the ability to go out to the Masjid(مسجد).
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ was carried to the Masjid(مسجد).
Where his head was wrapped because of his headache.
And he had to lean, he couldn't walk so he had to lean,
on one of the sons of Al-Abbas(العباس) and Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) to take him to the Masjid(مسجد).
And his feet were dragging on the ground because he couldn't lift them up.
And he went to the Masjid(مسجد) and he gave a Naseeha(نصيحه).
After praising Allahعَزّوجَلّ, Rasool Allah ﷺ mentioned the Shuhadaa(شهداء) of Uhud(أحَد),
and asked Allah to forgive them.
Notice here, Rasool Allah ﷺ, went to Al-Baqiyah(البقيه) to ask Allah to forgive the Muslims, who died in Al-Baqiyah(البقيه)
and now Rasool Allah ﷺ is asking forgiveness to the Shuhadaa(شهداء) of Uhud(أحَد).
This shows us, the loyalty that Rasool Allah ﷺ had to his companions,
the love that he had for them and remembrance is that he had for them.
Rasool Allah ﷺ was concerned about his Ummah(امة) .
Rasool Allah ﷺ lived for us,
he lived for me and you,
he gave his life for me and you,
he struggled,
he went through difficulties,
he suffered poverty,
he suffered pain,
he had to fight,
he had to go through trials and tribulations for the religion to reach me and you.
We owe Rasool Allah ﷺ a lot,
Rasool Allah ﷺ after mentioning the people of Uhud(أحَد)
then he was giving a Naseeha(نصِيْحَه) to the Muhajireen(مهاجرين).
He told them;
يا معشرَ المهاجِرينَ إنَّكم قَدْ أَصْبَحْتُم تزيدونَ وَ الْأَنْصَارُ عَلَى هَيْئْتِهَا لَا تَزِيْدُ
O, people of Al-Muhajiroon(مهاجرون),
The Muhajiroon(مهاجرون) are the ones, who made Hijrah(هجرة),
you are increasing in numbers while the Ansaar(أنصار) are not increasing in numbers.
That is because the population of Ansaar(أنصار) was the same,
while the Muhajireen(مهاجرين) are increasing because the Hijrah(هجرة) was not only from Quraish(قُرَيْشْ),
but it was now from all over Arabia.
So, the Muhajireen(مهاجرين) are now the majority of the population of Madina.
When in the beginning, the Muhajireen(مهاجرين) were very few in number
and the majority of the people in Madina were the locals, the people of Ansaar(أنصار).
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ is telling the Muhajireen(مهاجرين) that your numbers are adding up
while the Ansaar(أنصار) are not increasing and then he said;
وَاِنَّهُمْ عَيْبَتِيْ الَّتِيْ آوَيْتُ إِلَيْهَا فَأَكْرِمُوْا كَرِيْمَهُمْ وَتَجَاوَزُوْا عَنْ مُسِيْئِهِمْ
They are the ones, who supported me in the beginning so honor the honorable among them,
and forgive the ones among them, who make mistakes.
Rasool Allah ﷺ does not want to die and have the Ansaar(أنصار) suffer
because now they are a minority in Madina.
And Rasool Allah ﷺ is reminding the Muhajireen(مهاجرين) to take care of them,
the good among them, treat them very well.
And the ones among them will make mistakes forgive them.
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
اَيُّهَا النَّاسْ إِنَّ عَبْدًا مِّنْ عِبَادِ اللـه قَدْ خَيَّرَه’ اللـهُ بَيْنَ الدُّنْيَا وَبَيْنَ مَا عِنْدَ اللـه
There is a servant, O people from among the servants of Allah.
And Allah has given him the option of this world or what is in the hands of Allah.
That's all what Rasool Allah ﷺ said. He didn't indicate, who this slave of Allah is.
But Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) understood the meaning and he started to cry.
He understood that Rasool Allah ﷺ is talking about himself
because the Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء) of Allah are given the choice before they die
not like everybody else, the Angel of Death just comes to you unannounced,
the Angel of Death comes to the Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء) and seeks their permission to take their souls.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ is saying that
there's a slave of Allah, who was given the choice of Duniyah(دُنِيَّا) or Akhirah(آخره).
So, Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) cried and he told Rasool Allah ﷺ:
بَلْ نَحْنُ لَفْدِيْكَ بِأَنْفُسِنَا وَاَبْنَائِنَا
We will sacrifice ourselves and our children for you.
Rasool Allah ﷺ told him.
عَلَى رِسْلِكْ
Rasool Allah ﷺ stopped Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) and then told him, he told everyone.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
The person most faithful to myself in his friendship and his wealth is Abu Bakr(ابوبكر).
Rasool Allah ﷺ now, towards the end of his life is recognizing Abu Bakr رضي الله عنه in front of everyone
and letting the people know the status of Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه.
The person, most faithful to myself in his friendship, and his wealth is Abu Bakr(ابوبكر).
If I were to take any other than Allah, as a beloved one as a Khaleel(خليل), I would so take Abu Bakr(ابوبكر).
However, what I do have with him is the companionship of Islam and his love
every door in the mosque should be shut except that of Abu Bakr(ابوبكر).
Rasool Allah ﷺ said here, Khaleel(خليل), Khaleel(خليل) is a higher level than friend,
it is something that fills your heart with love.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: If I'm going to choose out of this world, a Khaleel(خليل), it would be Abu Bakr(ابوبكر).
But I am the Khaleel(خليل) of Allah and Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) is my brother and friend.
Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) is the one whom I share with him love.
Rasool Allah ﷺ gave some final advice to the Ummah(امة) in one Hadith(حديث) Rasool Allah ﷺ said:
لَعْنَ الله الْيَهُوْدَ والنَصَارَه اِتَّخَذُوْا قُبُوْرَ الأنْبِيَاءَ مَسَاجِدْ
May Allah curse the Jews and Christians for building Mosques over the graves of their Prophets.
They turned the graves of the prophets into Masajid(مساجد).
Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
لَا يبْقَى فِيْ جَزِيْرَةِ الْعَرَبِ دِيْنَانِ
No two religions should coexist in the Arabian Peninsula.
This is a Kuffr(كفر) free zone, the Arabian Peninsula should be purely Islamic.
No other religion should coexist with Islam in the Arabian Peninsula.
And this is one of the final words of advice of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
Rasool Allah ﷺ also said;
اُوْصِيْكُمْ بِالصَّلَاةْ
Rasool Allah is giving them the advice of Salah(صلاة).
Rasool Allah ﷺ also gave us advice to take care of the slaves,
Rasool Allah ﷺ repeated this advice to take care of the slaves, to take care of the slaves
and Rasool Allah ﷺ also said;
اِتَّقُوللهَ فِيْ النِسَاء
Fear Allah in the women.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ was giving the advice to the Ummah(امة), do not take advantage of the weak among the Ummah(امة)
and Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
مَا تَرَكَ قَوْمٌ الجِهَادْ إِلَّا ذِلُّوا
Whenever people leave Jihad(جهاد), they will be humiliated
and Rasool Allah ﷺ also ordered that the army of Osama(اسامه) should be sent out.
Because now the army of Osama(اسامه) was camping outside the Madina
until, all of the fighters, to get ready, and then they would set out.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ was saying;
اَنْفِذُوْا بَعَثَ اُسَامَه
Send out the army of Osama(اسامه).
Rasool Allah ﷺ was still going around, the houses of his wives.
But then eventually it was becoming difficult for him.
So, he was carried in to the house of Ayesha(عائشه).
And he gathered all of his wives and he sought their permission
to allow him to stay in the house of Ayesha(عائشه), while he is ill and they agreed.
So, Ayesha(عائشه) had Rasool Allah ﷺ in her house
and she was the one tending to him and she said: This the first time I tended to an ill person.
Rasool Allah ﷺ spent the rest of his life in the house of Ayesha رضي الله عنها,
or the end of his life was in the house of Ayesha رضي الله عنها.
Ayesha(عائشه), she said, that Rasool Allah ﷺ when he would become ill
he would recite the Maoozaat(معؤذات) in his hands
and then he would blow in them and then he would wipe his body.
But when he became ill, he could not do that for himself.
So, Ayesha(عائشه) would recite the Su'arr(سوّر) in the hands of Rasool Ullah
and then she would use his hands to wipe his body for him.
She would not do it, in her own hands, because the hands of Rasool Allah ﷺ are more blessed.
So, even though she would do the recitation, but she would not do it in her hands but in the hands of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
One day her brother, Abdur Rahman(عبد الرحمن) came in and he had a Miswaak(مسواك).
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ was staring at the Miswaak(مسواك),
so Ayesha(عائشه) understood that Rasool Allah ﷺ wants it.
So, she told him; Do you want it?
Rasool Allah ﷺ made a gesture that yes.
So she took it from Abdur Rahman(عبد الرحمن) and then she soften the other end,
and she gave it to Rasool Allah ﷺ.
And he used the Miswaak(مسواك), she said: As if he was healthy.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ, even though he was in the end of his life,
but he was not leaving the Sunnah(سنة) of Miswaak(مسواك).
Osama Bin Zaid(اسامه بن زيد) and the Muslims who were camping out of Madina,
they heard the news of the illness of Rasool Allah ﷺ, so they came back
and Osama(اسامه) came to visit Rasool Allah ﷺ.
And Rasool Ullah was ill to the extent that he could not speak
and then Osama(اسامه) said: Rasool Allah ﷺ raised his hands up
and then he would point to me, he would raise his hands up and then point to me.
Rasool Allah ﷺ was making Dua(دُعَا) for Osama(اسامه).
Osama(اسامه) said: Rasool Ullah, I understood that Rasool Allah ﷺ was making Dua(دُعَا) for me.
Rasool Allah ﷺ was in those difficult moments, the agony and pain of illness.
Nevertheless, he was making the Dua(دُعَا) for Osama Bin Zaid(اسامه بن زيد)
and this shows us how much Rasool Allah ﷺ loved Osama Bin Zaid رضي الله عنه.
Rasool Allah ﷺ could not go out and lead the Salah(صلاة) anymore.
So, he ordered that Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه should lead the Salah(صلاة).
مُرُوا أَبَا بَكْرٍ فَلْيُصَلِّ بِالنَّاسِ
Order Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) to lead the people in Salah(صلاة)
Ayesha(عائشه) did not want her father to lead the Salah(صلاة), so she said;
O Rasool Ullah, Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) is a very soft hearted man.
And I'm afraid that if he stands in your position, he would not be able to handle it
and he will not be able to complete the Salah(صلاة) meaning that
if he's in that position, he might become too emotional to continue the Salah(صلاة).
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
مُرُوا أَبَا بَكْرٍ فَلْيُصَلِّ بِالنَّاسِ
The objection of Ayesha(عائشه), was repeated again.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
مُرُوا أَبَا بَكْرٍ فَلْيُصَلِّ بِالنَّاس، إنَّكُنَّ صَوَیحبات يُوسُفَ
You women are the companions of Yusuf(يوسف).
And what Rasool Allah ﷺ meant by that the woman of Yousuf(يوسف) showed something but they were hiding something else.
When the wife of Al-Aziz(العزيز) invited all of those women to come,
she invited them Apparently, it is just a gathering.
But in reality, she wanted them there to see Yusuf(يوسف).
And Ayesha رضي الله عنها, her public statement was that my father is a soft hearted man so he won't be able to pray
but in reality, the reason why she didn't want her father to pray and she actually mentioned that.
she said: The reason I didn't want my father to pray is because people will dislike him
for standing in the place of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
I mean, people were used to having Rasool Allah lead them in Salah(صلاة)
And now they're having somebody else that might make them dislike the fact that Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) is in that place.
But Rasool Allah ﷺ says in another narration
because it says that Umar رضي الله عنه led the Salah(صلاة).
يأَبَی الله ذَالِكَ وَرَسُولُه’ وَالْمُؤمِنُوْنْ
Allah does not want that and Rasool Allah ﷺ does not want that and the believers, do not want that
it is Abu Bakr(ابوبكر), who must lead the Muslims in Salah(صلاة)
and this is also an indication that
the Imam(إمام) after Rasool Allah ﷺ is Abu Bakr As-Siddique(ابوبكر الصديق) in the issues of religion and in the issues of Duniyah(دُنِيَّا).
Rasool Allah ﷺ was now extremely tired because of his illness.
And he was not going out to the Salah(صلاة).
But on Monday when the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم were Salah(صلاة)
and they were being led by Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه,
Rasool Allah ﷺ uncovered the curtain that is between him and the Masjid(مسجد).
Anas Ibn Malik(انس ابن مالك) narrates he says and this is Bukhari(بخاريْ).
حتَّى إذَا كانَ يَوْمُ الِاثْنَيْنِ وهُمْ صُفُوفٌ في الصَّلَاةِ
When it was Monday and they were lined up, in Salah(صلاة).
فَكَشَفَ النبيُّ صَلَّى اللهُ عليه وسلَّمَ سِتْرَ الحُجْرَةِ
Rasool Allah ﷺ uncovered the curtain.
يَنْظُرُ إلَيْنَا وهو قَائِمٌ كَأنَّ وجْهَهُ ورَقَةُ مُصْحَفٍ،
Rasool Allah ﷺ took a look at us and he was standing up
And Anas Ibn Malik(انس ابن مالك) says; As if his face was a page out of a book.
Meaning clear and clean and beautiful and another narration;
كَأنَّ وجْهَهُ فلْقَ الْقَمَرْ
As if his face was part of the moon.
And then Anas Ibn Malik(انس ابن مالك) said;
ثُمَّ تَبَسَّمَ يَضْحَكُ
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ smiled, laughing.
فَهَمَمْنَا أنْ نَفْتَتِنَ مِنَ الفَرَحِ برُؤْيَةِ النبيِّ صَلَّى اللهُ عليه وسلَّمَ
It was almost going to be a Fitnah(فِتْنَه) for us because of our happiness, by seeing Rasool Allah ﷺ.
What he meant by Fitnah(فِتْنَه) is, that we were going to walk out of Salah(صلاة)
because we were in Salah(صلاة) and we saw that, and it is so beautiful and so much joy for us,
we're almost going to lose our Salah(صلاة).
And Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) was coming back, so that Rasool Allah ﷺ would lead the Salah(صلاة),
but Rasool Allah ﷺ had, Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) pray in his place.
However, Rasool Allah ﷺ did come out at a certain time
and He would sit down, but Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) would be standing up.
And some narration say that it was actually Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) leading the Salah(صلاة)
but others say that it was Rasool Ullah leading Abu Bakr(ابوبكر)
and Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) was standing and leading the rest.
Back to this narration of Anas Ibn Malik رضي الله عنه,
he said that the face of Rasool Allah ﷺ, when he saw them, he was smiling with joy. Why?
And by the way, this is the last scene that Rasool Allah ﷺ sees from his Ummah(امة),
the last thing that Rasool Allah ﷺ saw, from his Ummah(امة)
was them in Salah(صلاة), in Salaah-Tul-Jama'ah(صلاة الجماعة).
Brothers and sisters, when you are praying to Allahعَزّوجَلّ
and for the brothers whom Salaah-Tul-Jama'ah(صلاة الجماعة) is Wajib(واجب) on them.
When you are in Salaah-Tul-Jama'a(صلاة الجماعة), this is a site that pleases Rasool Ullah صلوات الله وسلام عليه.
When Rasool Allah ﷺ uncovered that curtain.
He saw the result, he saw the fruit of his effort and his Daw'ah(دعوة).
The Muslims are lining up in Salah(صلاة) the most important deed in Islam after
أَشْهَدُ أَنْ لَا إِلَهَ إِلَّا اللَّهُ وَأَشْهَدُ أَنَّ مُحَمَّدًارَسُولُ الله  ‫‬
And Rasool Allah ﷺ smiled with happiness, because Rasool Allah ﷺ was now seen standing up,
they assumed that the Rasool Allah ﷺ has become better.
So, Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) sought permission to go to As-Sun'hh(ألصنح),
where his other wife was, which was a little bit outside of Madina
because he was tied up in Madina due to the illness of Rasool Allah ﷺ
but now he thought that Rasool Allah ﷺ is better, so he left.
And Al-Abbas(العباس), he met Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) after he came out from the house of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
And this is in Al-Bukhari(بخاريْ), He met with Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) and he told him;
يَا أبَا لْحَسَنٍ، كيفَ أصْبَحَ رَسولُ اللَّهِ صَلَّى اللهُ عليه وسلَّمَ؟
How is Rasool Allah ﷺ doing, this morning.?
So, Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) said;
أصْبَحَ بحَمْدِ اللَّهِ بَارِئًا
He looks with the praise of Allah much better.
Al-Abbas(العباس) grabbed the hand of Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) and told him;
أنْتَ واللَّهِ بَعْدَ ثَلَاثٍ عبدُ العَصَا
After three days from now, you would be a slave ruled by a stick.
What does Al-Abbas(العباس) mean by this, you would be a slave ruled by a stick,
meaning that you would be a person without any authority.
You would be a follower, without any authority.
And this is Farasah(فراسه) of Al-Abbas Bin Abdul Muttalib رضي الله عنه.
Farasah(فراسه) is intuition.
Al-Abbas(العباس) said;
إنِّي وَلله لَأَعْرِفُ اَلْمَوْتْ فِيْ وُجُوهِ بَنِي عبدِ المُطَّلِب
Al-Abbas(العباس) said: I can read death in the faces of the sons of Abdul Muttalib(عبد المطلب).
And I can see death in the face of Rasool Ullah,
everybody was thinking that Rasool Allah was better.
Al-Abbas(العباس) said: No.
I recognize death in my family, I can see it, in their faces.
And I can actually see it now in the face of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
And I think that Rasool Ullah would die pretty soon.
Al-Abbas(العباس) doesn't know the unseen, death is something that only Allah knows.
But Al-Abbas(العباس) has this intuition, where he could recognize
when the sons of Abdul Muttalib(عبد المطلب) are approaching their death.
So, he told Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب);
Go and ask Rasool Allah ﷺ,
if we are going to be in authority of the Ummah(امة) after him.
Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) refused and he said;
I will not ask him that because if he rejects that, then the Ummah(أمة) will not give it to us, to the end of time.
And Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) refused to go and talk to Rasool Allah ﷺ about this.
Anyway, there was a very steep deterioration in the situation of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
And within that day, that same day, which is Monday now,
Rasool Allah ﷺ has been ill now, for about 13 days,
Rasool Allah ﷺ started going through Saqraat-Ul-Maot(سقراة الموت).
Saqraat-Ul-Maot(سقراة الموت) are the final moments, the agony of death, when the soul is coming out.
So, Ayesha(عائشه) brought some water for Rasool Allah and he would soak a piece of cloth in that water,
and then he would wipe his face with it and say;
اِنَّ لِلْمَوْتِ لَسَكرَاتْ
There's agony in death, there's agony in death.
Rasool Allah ﷺ himself, the best of the creation have to go through this.
And he was in the lap of Ayesha رضي الله عنها.
And Ayesha(عائشه) said: Rasool Allah ﷺ looked up towards the roof with his eyes.
And I heard him say;
بَلِّ الرَّفيقَ الأَعْلى، بَلِّ الرَّفيقَ الأَعْلى، بَلِّ الرَّفيقَ الأَعْلى
No! The highest companion, the highest companion, the highest companion,
Ayesha رضي الله عنها said: I knew that Rasool Allah ﷺ was being asked by the angel of death,
whether he wants to stay with us or to leave.
And Rasool Allah ﷺ was saying: I want to be with the highest companion, and that is Allahعَزّوجَلّ.
And then Ayesha(عائشه) says; The head of Rasool Allah ﷺ turned towards me.
And she screamed, in the narration of Ibn Hishaam(إبن هشام);
وَمِنْ حمقي وَقِلَّة عَقْلِيْ
Because of my foolishness, I screamed, and I yelled
and now the news spreading around Madina like fire.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab رضي الله عنه and Al-Mugheerah(المغيره) rushed in into the room
and Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) said;
مَا اَشَدّ مَا غَشِيَّ عَلَيْهْ
Rasool Allah ﷺ is unconsciousness, and this is severe unconsciousness.
And when they were walking out Al-Mugheerah(المغيره) told Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب);
لَقَدْ تُوُّفِيَّ رَسُولُ الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
Rasool Allah ﷺ is dead.
This is not unconsciousness, Rasool Allah ﷺ is dead.
You know, brothers and sisters, we cannot imagine how this news was on the Sahabah(صحابه)
because we don't have that same love.
We did not live with Rasool Allah ﷺ for years.
Rasool Allah ﷺ for them was everything.
He was their leader, he was like their father to them.
He was an advisor to them, he was their teacher, he was everything.
So, Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) when he heard, Al-Mugheerah(المغيره) say, that Rasool Allah ﷺ died.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) said;
اِنَّكَ رَجُلٌ تَحُوْسُكَ فِتْنَه
You are a man of Fitnah(فِتْنَه) or you are a man who wants to bring dissension among the Ummah(امة).
Rasool Allah ﷺ did not die because he will not die until the exterminate the Munafiqeen(منافقين).
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) understood that Rasool Allah ﷺ will not die
until all of the Munafiqeen(منافقين) are killed.
And then Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) rushed out to the Masjid(مسجد)
and the people were starting to come in crowds in the Masjid(مسجد) and there was weeping everywhere.
Everyone was crying, and Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) drew out his sword and said;
there are some Munafiqeen(منافقين), who are claiming that Rasool Allah ﷺ died.
Rasool Allah ﷺ did not die but Rasool Allah ﷺ is unconscious like Musa(موسى) became unconscious,
and he will come back and he will kill all of the Munafiqeen(منافقين).
And whoever says that Rasool Allah ﷺ is dead,
I'm going to cut off his head with the sword of mine.
The news reached Abu Bakr رضي الله عنه and he came back from As-Sun'hh(ألصنح) on his horse.
And he did not speak to anyonen and he came into the room of Ayesha(عائشه).
With Rasool Allah ﷺ covered with cloth.
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه uncovered the face of Rasool Allah ﷺ and when he saw him, he cried.
And then he kissed Rasool Allah ﷺ and said;
You are pure, when alive and you are a pure when dead.
In the name of Allah, Allah will not make you die twice.
And the death that was prescribed on you, the death that is ordained on you and everybody else, you have went through it.
So, now that's it.
You have went through the death that's prescribed on you.
And then Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) came out of the room of Ayesha(عائشه) and went to the Masjid(مسجد)
and, Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) a was screaming and yelling and threatening.
So Abu Bakr As-Siddique(ابوبكر الصديق), told Umar(عمر),
إِجْلِسْ يَا عُمر
sit down Umar(عمر)! Umar(عمر) ignored Abu Bakr(ابوبكر).
He told him, sit down Umar(عمر)! A second time and Umar(عمر) is carrying on.
So, Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) then, started speaking
and people just left Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) and came to listen to, what Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه had to say.
Abu Bakr رضي الله عنه said;
مَن كانَ يَعْبُدُ مُحَمَّدًا فإنَّ مُحَمَّدًا قدْ مَاتَ، ومَن كانَ يَعْبُدُ اللَّهَ فإنَّ اللَّهَ حَيٌّ لَا يَمُوتُ
Whoever used to worship Muhammad(محمد), then know that Muhammad(محمد) is dead,
and whoever used to worship Allah, then know that Allah is alive and he would never die.
And then he recited the Ayah(آية).
وَمَا مُحَمَّدٌ إِلَّا رَسُولٌ قَدْ خَلَتْ مِنْ قَبْلِهِ الرُّسُلُ ۚ أَفَإِنْ مَاتَ أَوْ قُتِلَ انْقَلَبْتُمْ عَلَىٰ أَعْقَابِكُمْۚ
وَمَنْ يَنْقَلِبْ عَلَىٰ عَقِبَيْهِ فَلَنْ يَضُرَّ اللَّهَ شَيْئًا ۗ وَسَيَجْزِي اللَّهُ الشَّاكِرِينَ۝
Muhammad(محمد) is not, but a Messenger, other Messengers have passed on before him.
So, if he was to die or be killed would you turn back on your heels, to unbelief
and he, who turns back on his heels, will never harm Allah at all but Allah will reward, the Grateful.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) said: Is this Ayah(آية) in the book of Allah.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) already knows the Ayah(آية)
but Subhaan Allah(سبحان الله), it is, as if he heard it, for the first time.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) said: I realized that Muhammadﷺ was dead.
فَعَقَرْتْ فَمَا تَكِلِّنِيْ رَجِلَيْكْ
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) collapsed and said my feet cannot carry me anymore.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) the strong, powerful man could not handle the news,
it was like an arrow that struck his heart,
and he fell down because his knees could not carry him anymore.
And the narrators says;
فَمَا سمع بَشَرٌمِّنَّ النَّاسِ اِلَّا يَتْلُوْهَا
Everyone was reciting this Ayah(آية), as if they heard it for the first time.
We will skip the event of the Bay'yah(بيعة) to Abu Bakr(ابو بكر)
because I already talked about it, in the beginning of the lectures on Abu Bakr As-Siddique(ابو بكر الصديق).
We'll move on to the washing of Rasool Allah ﷺ and how, his burial?
Ibn Abbas رضي الله عنه said that the family of Rasool Allah ﷺ
are the ones, who took care of the washing of the body of Rasool Allah ﷺ
and those were Al-Abbas Bin Abdul Muttalib(العباس ابن عبد المطلب)
and Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) and Fazal Bin Abbas(فضل بن عاس), Kizm Bin Al-Abbas(كظم بن عباس)
and Osama Bin Zaid(اسامه بن زيد) and Salih(صالح) the servant of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
And then Aos Bin Khaoli(أوس بن خولي), one of Ansaar(أنْصَار) he knocked on the door
and told Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب), I ask you in the name Allah to allow me in.
So, he was allowed in, but he did not participated in the actual washing.
Ali(علي) had the body of Rasool Allah ﷺ, on his chest.
And it is said, in a narration that they were debating whether to wash Rasool Allah ﷺ with his clothes or without his clothes
because the Sunnah(سنة) is to wash without the clothes.
But then they heard a sound telling them to wash Rasool Ullah with his clothes.
So, the body of Rasool Allah ﷺ was not uncovered, during his washing.
Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) said: We washed him, from over his garments.
And  Al-Abbas(العباس), Fazal(فضل) and Kizam(كظم) used to turn the body around for, with Ali(علي)
and Usama bin Zaid(اسامه بن زيد) and Saleh(صالح) the servant of Rasool Ullah were the ones pouring the water.
And Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) was the one, who would rub the body of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
And then, they put him in three pieces of cloth which were the shroud,
that was the shroud of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
The Salah(صلاة) of Janazah(جنازه) on Rasool Allah ﷺ, it wasn't one congregation
but people would come in and pray and then they would come out.
And this carried on, men would come in and out as much as the room would fit.
making Salah-Janazah(صلاة جنازه) on Rasool Allah ﷺ.
And the body of Rasool Allah ﷺ was in the room of Ayesha رضي الله عنها.
And Umm Salamah(أم سلمه) says: We were all together, the women of Rasool Ullah crying,
and we had the little comfort in seeing, at least the body of Rasool Allah ﷺ,
even if Rasool Allah was not alive, we had the body of Rasool Allah ﷺ to look at, with us in the room,
and we are crying, continuously crying.
And then Subhaan Allah(سبحان الله), she said and this is Wednesday night, late at night.
She said: We heard the pickaxes, we heard the digging,
the digging of the grave of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
We all broke down and screamed and they heard it in the Masjid(مسجد)
and they screamed and all of Madina, there was an uproar in all of Madina.
Because now they know that the body of Rasool Allah ﷺ is going into His grave.
She said: They heard us, in the Masjid(مسجد)
and then from the Masjid(مسجد), the crying was everywhere all over Madina.
And when it was time for Fajar(فجر) Bilal(بلال) was making Azaan(اذان).
He said: Allah Ho Akbar(الله اكبر), Allah Ho Akbar(الله اكبر), Allah Ho Akbar(الله اكبر), Allah Ho Akbar(الله اكبر)
اشهدوالله اله الا الله ،, اشهدوالله اله الا الله
And when he came to
اشهد اَنَّ محمد رسول الله
And he could not go any further, he started crying and could not finish the Azaan(اذان).
So, they dug the grave of Rasool Allah ﷺ in the room of Ayesha(عائشه),
according to the Sunnah(سنه), that the Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء) are buried in the place where they died
and Rasool Allah ﷺ was buried in the room of Ayesha رضي الله عنه.
Ayesha(عائشه) said, that she saw a dream that three moons fell in her lap.
So, Abu Bakr As-Siddique(ابو بكر الصديق) and he was very good at dream interpretations.
He said: If your dream is true, then three men from the best men on the face of the earth, would be buried in your house.
And when it was time to burry Rasool Allah ﷺ.
Abu Bakr(ابو بكر) told Ayesha رضي الله عنها this is the best of your moons.
The body of Rasool Allah ﷺ was descended into the grave
and again it was the family of Rasool Allah ﷺ that took care of his burial.
However, it says in one narration, that Al-Mugheerah(المغيره) before they would cover the grave.
He threw in, his ring intentionally into the grave.
And then he told everyone, wait, wait, let me go and grab my ring.
So, he went down to the grave to be the last person, who would touch Rasool Allah ﷺ, and then it came out.
When the burial was done and people came back.
Fatima رضي الله عنها said: يَا اَنَسْ
She is speaking to Anas Ibn Malik(انس ابن مالك), she said;
يا أنَسُ أطَابَتْ أنْفُسُكُمْ أنْ تَحفی التُّرَابَ علَى رَسولِ اللَّهِ
Did your heart allow you to throw dirt on the body of Rasool Allah ﷺ when he was buried.
So, the whole thing was difficult for them,
the washing of Rasool Ullah, the burial of Rasool Ullah, the death of Rasool Ullah,
everything was it was very difficult on the Ummah(امة).
And that's why, Rasool Allah ﷺ says;
Whenever a calamity befalls one of you, remember the calamity of my death,
the greatest calamity that can befall a Muslim has already happened,
and that is the death of Rasool Allah ﷺ, whatever happens to you after that is going to be small
compared to the loss of Rasool Allah ﷺ,
compared to the fact that Rasool Allah ﷺ is not with us.
Everything else is small.
And there was Fitnah(فتنه) after the death of Rasool Ullah صلوات الله وسلام عليه.
Many of the tribes became Murtadd(مرتد).
Muhammad Ibn Is'haaq(إسحاق محمد ابن) says;
وَلَمَّا توُفِّيَ رسولُ اللَّهِ صلَّى اللَّهُ عليهِ وسلَّمَ ارتدَّتِ العربُ
The Arabs became apostate.
وَاشْرَأَبّتْ الْيَهُودِيّةُ والنصرانية
And Jews and Christians started showing themselves again.
وَنَجَمَ النّفَاقُ
And hypocrisy became very widespread.
وَصَارَ الْمُسْلِمُونَ كَالْغَنَمِ الْمَطِيرَةُ فِي اللّيْلَةِ الشّاتِيَةِ لِفَقْدِ نَبِيّهِمْ
And Muslims were like lost sheep in a cold rainy night after the Prophet Rasool Allah ﷺ died,
حَتّى جَمَعَهُمْ اللهُ عَلَى أَبِي بَكْرٍالصديق
Until they were brought together again, under Abu Bakr(ابوبكر).
And Anas Ibn Malik رضي الله عنه says: I witnessed two days in my life.
One of them was the best day and one of them was the worst day.
The best day was the day when Rasool Allah ﷺ came to Madina.
And that was a day when everything was bright.
And then the worst day was the day Rasool Allah ﷺ passed away and that was a dark day.
Anas Ibn Malik(انس ابن مالك) also says;
ومَا نَفَذنَا عَنْ رسولِ اللَّهِ صلَّى اللَّهُ عليْهِ وسلَّمَ اَلْأَيْدِيَ حَتَّى أنْكَرْنَا قُلُوْبَنَا
By the time we were dusting our hands after the burial of Rasool Allah ﷺ,
we would already feel that our hearts are different.
The hearts were different because of death of Rasool Ullah صلوات الله وسلام عليه.
One day Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) and Umar(عمر) decided to visit Umm Aimen(ام ايمن).
She started to cry and they told her, Why are you crying?
She said: I'm crying because there is no more revelation.
So, it was not only Rasool Allah ﷺ that, they were missing
but they were also missing the revelation that was coming from As-Samawaat(أسماواة).
I mean, imagine living in a time when Qur'an was being revealed,
Ayaat(آيات) you're going to hear for the first time in your life.
What did Rasool Allah ﷺ leave behind?
Rasool Allah ﷺ did not leave behind any inheritance.
Rasool Allah ﷺ lived for his Ummah(امة).
Lived, serving Allahعَزّوجَلّ and Rasool Allah ﷺ passed away from this Duniyah(دُنِيَّا) clean.
He only left behind a white Mule and his weapons
and a land that he left behind for the travelers, as Sadaqah(صدقه), that's all what Rasool Allah ﷺ had.
His arms, which he used to fight Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله) and that's it.
No property, no land, no wealth, no gold and no silver, A Mule and arms.
Muhammad Ibn Is'haq(إسحاق محمد ابن) says: Rasool Allah ﷺ passed away on the 12th of Rabi-Ul-Awwal(ربيع اول).
same day in which he made Hijrah(هجرة) to Madina, 10 years ago.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ lived for exactly 10 years, in Madina.
Rasool Allah ﷺ died at the age of 63,
Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) died at the age of 63, and Umar(عمر) died at the age of 63.
They followed the footsteps of Rasool Ullah even in his death.
Brothers and sisters, this is the end of the Seerah(سيرة) of Rasool Ullah صلوات الله وسلام عليه.
We thank Allahعَزّوجَلّ, we say, Al-Hamdolillah(ألحمدلله, ألحمدلله, ألحمدلله)
who allowed us to go through the life, the Seerah(سيرة) of the best of creation, Muhammad صلوات الله وسلام عليه.
It is a wonderful time to spend with the story of our beloved Prophet.
So, we asked Allahعَزّوجَلّ, dear brothers and sisters in the end
to make us of those, who love Rasool Allah ﷺ,
to make us of those who truly love Rasool Allah ﷺ,
to make us of those, who will follow his Sunnah(سنة), his way.
And to the make us of those, who would be raised up with him on the day of judgment
and will drink from his hands, from Al-Kausar(ألكوثر).
We asked Allahعَزّوجَلّ to admit us with him into paradise.
Brothers and sisters, review the seerah(سيرة) of Rasool Allah ﷺ, hear it again.
Follow it and love Muhammadﷺ, and be concerned about the Ummah(امة),
like Rasool Allah ﷺ was concerned about the Ummah(امة).
Remember that Rasool Allah ﷺ lived and died for you.
Remember that Rasool Allah ﷺ, left a lot of the enjoyment of the Duniyah(دُنِيَّا) for the sake of having Islam come to you
and say Al-Hamdolillah(ألحمدالله) about that and be grateful, be grateful.
The one who is not grateful towards people, will not be grateful towards Allah.
And who among all humanity do we owe more to than Rasool Allah ﷺ,
we owe a lot to Rasool Allah ﷺ.
Everything that we know about Islam came to us through him.
How much do we owe to Rasool Allah صلوات الله وسلام عليه.
The least that we could do in recognition for what Rasool Allah ﷺ did for us, is that we follow him
and make Salah(صلاة) and Salaam(سلام) on Rasool Ullah صلوات الله وسلام عليه.
اَللَّهُمَّ صَلِّ علَى مُحَمَّدٍ وعلَى آلِ مُحَمَّدٍ، كَمَا صَلَّيْتَ علَى آلِ إبْرَاهِيمَ
وَ بَارِكْ علَى مُحَمَّدٍ وعلَى آلِ مُحَمَّدٍ، كَمَا بَارَكْتَ علَى إبْرَاهِيمَ، وعلَى آلِ إبْرَاهِيمَ إنَّكَ حَمِيدٌ مَجِيدٌ
وَالسلام عليكم ورحمة الله وبركاته